https://youtu.be/TGofLedD7RQ
https://youtu.be/TGofLedD7RQ
Culture in Shinjuku in the late 1960s was incredibly chaotic and energetic.
Văn hóa ở Shinjuku cuối những năm 1960 rất hỗn loạn.
Many performers, activists, artists, and avant garde people
Nhiều diễn viên, nhà hoạt động xã hội, nghệ sĩ
gathered in Shinjuku.
cùng những người tiên phong khác tập trung tại Shinjuku.
And they performed different type of cultural and political activities
Họ tổ chức các hoạt động văn hóa và chính trị khác nhau
around the Shinjuku Station area.
xung quanh ga Shinjuku.
One of the representative images of Shinjuku in those days
Có thể thấy những hình ảnh đặc trưng cho Shinjuku thời ấy
can be seen in the film of Nagisa Oshima.
thông qua bộ phim của Nagisa Oshima.
Nagisa Oshima is one of the most famous avant garde, or New Wave,
Nagisa Oshima là một trong những làn sóng mới,
film directors in those days.
đạo diễn phim nổi tiếng nhất thời ấy.
One of his films, directed by him in 1960, titled Night and Fog in Japan,
Một trong số đó được chỉ đạo bởi ông năm 1960 với tiêu đề Night and Fog in Japan,
criticized Japanese hypocrisy in the 1960s
đã phê phán thói đạp đức giả của người Nhật những năm 1960,
US-Japan treaty-- Security Treaty.
trong hiệp ước An ninh Mỹ-Nhật.
And also, in 1968, he directed Death by Hanging,
Năm 1968, ông làm đạo diễn phim Death by Hanging,
and he also criticized the issue of Koreans in Japanese society.
đồng thời phê phán hiện trạng người Hàn sống trong xã hội Nhật.
In his films, he uses images of murder, and violence, and rape,
Trong các bộ phim của mình, ông thường dùng các hình ảnh giết chóc, bạo lực
and act of blackmail, and so on.
cưỡng bức và tống tiền.
He used the image of violence to indict the hypocrisy of this society.
Ông dùng hình ảnh bạo lực để lên án thói đạo đức giả trong xã hội
One of his masterpieces about the city was Diary of a Shinjuku Thief.
Một trong những tuyệt tác về thành thị của ông là phim Diary of a Shinjuku Thief.
This film was directed in 1969.
Phim được ông đạo diễn năm 1969,
His film shows the image of Shinjuku in relation
phản ánh hình ảnh Shinjuku trong mối quan hệ với
with the sexual dynamics of the people who gather in this city.
hoạt động tình dục sôi nổi của những người sống trong thành phố.
In this film, many important artists and performers
Nhiều nghệ sĩ chủ chốt
and other kind of important cultural people appeared in the film.
cùng  người từ các tầng lớp văn hóa khác xuất hiện trong phim.
So this film is a very good example to understand the atmosphere of Shinjuku
Cho nên bộ phim là một ví đụ điển hình để cảm nhận
in the late 1960s from today.
không khí của Shinjuku cuối những năm 1960.
In this film, Juro Kara appeared as an actor, almost naked,
Trong phim, Juro Kara xuất hiện gần như khỏa thân
was wearing only a loincloth.
chỉ mặc một cái khố.
He was a very famous theater director also, in those days.
Ông cũng là một đạo diễn sân khấu nổi tiếng thời ấy,
He organized Jokyo Gekijo Theater.
thành lập rạp Jokyo Gekijo.
It is one of the representative theaters in the 1960s.
một trong những rạp chiếu tiêu biểu những năm 1960.
And he performed many plays around Shinjuku-- Hanazono Shrine, and Western
Ông đã biểu diễn rất nhiều vở kịch tại Shinjuku-- Hanazono Shrine
Shinjuku Central Park, and so on.
và công viên trung tâm Shinjuku.
So he was already very popular, and he was
Ông ấy đã rất nổi tiếng rồi và trở thành
one of the representative avant garde artists in Shinjuku.
một trong những nghệ sĩ tiên phong ở Shinjuku.
Also, in this film, Tadanori Yokoo, a very famous artist, painter,
Cũng trong phim này, Tadanori Yokoo, một nghệ sĩ, họa sĩ, nhà thiết kế nổi tiếng
and designer, appears as a spectator on the street wearing his sweater.
xuất hiện như người qua đường trong chiếc áo len dài
And he also collaborated with Judo Kara and Shuji Terayama,
Ông hợp tác với Judo Kara, Shuji Terayama
many of the avant garde artists in Shinjuku.
cùng nhiều nghệ sĩ tiên phong ở Shinjuku.
So in Shinjuku, there's some kind of connection
Ở Shinjuku, liên hệ giữa các nghệ sĩ,
between artists and activists, and many spectators,
các nhà hoạt động xã hội và những người quan sát
also-- have close relationship, or they share the atmosphere
khá thân thiết hoặc cùng chia sẻ bầu không khí
of this area very much in those days.
tại nơi đây
In this film, later, also Moichi Tanabe, he's
Trong phim, Moichi Tanabe,
a founder of Kinokuniya Book Store-- appeared, and he speak something.
người thành lập hiệu sách Kinokuniya cũng xuất hiện với vài lời thoại.
Moichi Tanabe is also an important culturalist, or cultural person,
Moichi Tanabe cũng là một nhà văn hóa quan trọng tại Shinjuku
in Shinjuku, who supported many cultural performance in this district.
ông ủng hộ nhiều màn biểu diễn văn hóa tại quân này.
Also, Kinokuniya Book Store is an important cultural space
Hiệu sách Kinokuniya cũng là không gian văn hóa có giá trị
where many new knowledge and movement started.
nơi khởi đầu nhiều tri thức mới và biến động
So in Shinjuku, many different types of artists and people
Ở Shinjuku, nhiều thành phần nghệ sĩ
gathered and interacted, and made some kind of intimate network
tập trung lại và tương tác với nhau
with each other.
tạo ra một số mạng lưới thân thiết.
And not only this kind of human networks,
Không chỉ những mạng lưới này
but also, in Shinjuku, there are many important cultural spaces,
mà còn nhiều không gian văn hóa khác tại Shinjuku
including Fugetsudo, Art Theater in Shinjuku Bunka, Shinjuku Art Village,
như Fugetsudo, Nhà hát nghệ thuật ở Shinjuku Bunka, làng nghệ thuật Shinjuku,
Shinjuku Pit Inn, and Shinjuku Golden Street, and so on.
Shinjuku Pit Inn và Shinjuku Golden Street.
Fugetsudo was one of the important coffee
Fugetsudo là mốt trong những quán cà phê quan trọng
shops where many avant garde artists and young people gathered,
nơi các nghệ sĩ mới cùng những người trẻ tập trung lại
and they discussed very intensively.
thảo luận sôi nổi
Also, Art Theater Shinjuku Bunka was a very famous movie theater,
Shinjuku Bunka cũng là một rạp chiếu nổi tiếng
where many avant garde movies were projected.
công chiếu nhiều bộ phim mới
And also, Shinjuku Art Village is a small, avant garde theater,
Shinjuku Art Village là một rạp nhỏ, mới
and Shinjuku Pit Inn is a jazz club, or music club, in Shinjuku.
còn Shinjuku Pit Inn là một câu lạc bộ nhạc jazz ở Shinjuku.
Shinjuku Golden Street still exists, and is famous for small drinking bars
Shinjuku Golden Street vẫn tồn tại, nổi tiếng với
and restaurants.
các quán rượu và nhà hàng.
One of the most prominent groups of artists and activists
Một trong những nhóm nghệ sĩ và nhà hoạt động nổi bật nhất
was called Folk Guerrilla.
là Folk Guerrilla.
Folk Guerrilla is the name of the people who gathered
Folk Guerrilla là tên của nhóm người
underground plaza of Shinjuku Station.
tập trung ở quảng trường ngầm của ga Station.
And they started songs, many songs, with folk guitar, in 1969 and '70s.
Họ biểu diễn các ca khúc với đàn ghi ta dân gian năm 1969 và những năm 1970
We have one documentary film, which shows
Tôi có một cuốn phim tài liệu
the image of Folk Guerrilla in it.
ghi lại hình ảnh của Folk Guerrilla.
This documentary film was directed by Ouchida Keiya.
Phim được đạo diễn bởi Ouchida Keiya.
He's a documentary director.
Ông là một đạo diễn phim tài liệu.
He directed some of the activist films, including Matsuyama Incident
Ông cũng chỉ đạo một số phim hành động gồm Matsuyama Incident
and some of the others.
và một số phim khác.
One of his films, titled Shinjuku Nishiguchi Chika Hiroba,
Một trong số đó như Shinjuku Nishiguchi Chika Hiroba,
Underground Plaza of Western Shinjuku, was a very important and impressive
Underground Plaza of Western Shinjuku,
documentary of Shinjuku in those days.
là một phim tài liệu rất ấn tượng về Shinjuku thời ấy.
So let's show the film together.
Vậy chúng ta cùng xem.